Good morning,
my name is Dan Margulis. Today's the 26th of תמוז Tammuz and
it is Monday morning. I am filling in for Rabbi Linzer as
he remains on vacation until I think this weekend.
Hope he's enjoying himself. We are going to be starting towards the
bottom of מ"ט עמוד ב'. Mem Tet Amud Bet. We had just
left off with three different stories about רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, about
how people asked him why his face was so shining and bright,
or yellow, the word is צהוב. tzahov. It could be sort of
yellowish, but probably not yellowish, probably means he was glowing, he was
radiant.
And so the first one of his רבנן rabbanan asked him why,
and he answered with a reasonably sort of more modest approach. A
rich woman asked him and he was able to give her a
different answer. And then a צדוקי, Tzeduki, a Sadducee, asked him and
he gave him a very brisk answer to shove him off. So
from there, we are on the
seventh line from the bottom,
sorry, sixth line from the bottom, and it says רבי יהודה כד
אזל לבי מדרשא. Rabbi Yehuda kad azal lebei midrasha. So רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda would bring a כד, kad, would bring a barrel, a
jug of some kind to the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. שקיל גופא
על כתפיה, shakil gufa al katfeih, אמר גדולה מלאכה שמכבדת את בעליה.
amar gedola melacha shemechabedet et be'aleha.
He says, and he would really schlepp it on his shoulders because
he says מלאכה, melacha, hard work, is a very good thing because
it brings honor to those who are doing the work. So sounds
like sort of strange, he's just bringing something to sit on to
the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. He's bringing his chair, he's bringing his
shtender. It's not so clear why that's such a big מלאכה melacha
that's going to be contributing so much כבוד kavod to him as
opposed to having a job, but that's what he says. He says
מלאכה, melacha, that was sort of his proof that מלאכה מכבדת את
בעליה. melacha mechabedet et be'aleha. Okay. דביתהו דרבי יהודה נפקת עמרא, deveitehu
deRabbi Yehuda nafkut amra, so
the wife of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda went and got this wool,
עבדה גלימא, avda glima,
so she went and made a shirt for him or some kind
of a cloak. דהות בה כד נפקא לשוקא מיכסיא ביה, dehuteva kad
nafka leshuka michasya beih,
so when she would go out into the שוקא shuka she would
wear it, וכד נפק רבי יהודה לצלויי הוה מיכסיא ומצלי. vechad nafak
Rabbi Yehuda letzaluya hava michasya umatzli.
And when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would go to go pray, he
would use that as his garment. So this is at first glance
meant to tell us a bit about the austerity, the poverty that
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda lived with, that he and his wife were
sharing the same cloak. She would wear it when she had to
go out to the שוקא shuka and he would wear it when
he would go davening. It's an interesting question for the הלכה halacha
about בגד איש ובגד אשה beged ish uveged isha because how can
it be that there's this one cloak that they would both share?
So it sounds like this is a proof that a unisex garment,
something that has no real intention for either a man or a
woman, would be permitted for both men and women to wear because
we see from רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and his wife that they
shared the same cloak. וכד מיכסי ביה הוה מברך ברוך שעטני מעיל,
vechad michasei beih hava mevarech Baruch she'atani me'il,
and when he would wear it, when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would
wear it, he would say a ברכה, bracha, ברוך שעטני מעיל, Baruch
she'atani me'il, Blessed is God who has wrapped me with this cloak.
It's an interesting point. Number one, this is a different נוסח הברכה
nusach habracha from the other ברכה bracha that we know about when
you wear new clothes or fancy clothing. The other point to note
is this is the proof used by the רא"ש Rosh in ברכות
Berachot to prove that when a person buys new clothing and wants
to say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu ברכה bracha or wants to say מלביש ערומים
Malbish Arumim on a new piece of clothing, that that's very subjective.
It's based on what's valuable to you. So for רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda who was rather poor, this simple cloak that his wife had
made him brought him a lot of enjoyment and he really wanted
to, he was very excited to wear it and that was a
good enough reason to say the ברכה bracha even though it was
something that might not have been valued highly by other people. Okay.
זמנא חדא גזר רבי שמעון בן גמליאל תעניתא. zimna chada gazar Rabbi
Shimon ben Gamliel ta'anita. One time רבי שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabbi Shimon
ben Gamliel,
who was the נשיא nasi of the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, so he established
that there should be a fast day, presumably because of lack of
rain, it was a drought, that was most of the reason why
we have fast days as we saw in מסכת תענית. Masechet Ta'anit.
So רבי יהודה לא אתא לבי תעניתא. Rabbi Yehuda lo ata lebei
ta'anita.
So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda did not come to the fasting house.
It sounds like when they would gather all of the people together,
so that's really he didn't show up for the fast and he
didn't show up to the public gathering. We know from מסכת תענית
Masechet Ta'anit that they used to have public gathering in the town
square, they would bring the ספר תורה Sefer Torah into the town
square and have the davening there, both to accommodate more people than
generally came to shul otherwise and also to have it be more
of a public spectacle. אמרו ליה לית ליה כסויא,
amru leih leit
leih kisuya, so they told him. that he, he רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda does not have a כסות, ksut, he doesn't have a garment,
a clothing. It's interesting to note the difference between a בגד beged
and a כסות, ksut, some people have tried to argue, I listened
to a שיעור shiur recently, the difference that the חיוב chiyuv in
ציצית tzitzit applies from the פסוק pasuk in דברים Devarim applies, it
says על ארבע כנפות כסותך אשר תכסה בה, al arba kanfot ksutecha
asher tichaseh bah, the wrap, the outer cloak that you wrap over
yourself is different from a בגד, beged, a בגד beged is more
like the inner tunic and the כסות ksut is an overcoat. And
so some people want to argue from that that the טלית קטן
tallit katan that many people have a custom to wear is not
necessarily really fulfilling the obligation of ציצית tzitzit in the same way
as a טלית גדול. tallit gadol.
There's some argument back and forth about that, but that's the word
כסות ksut that it's the outer cloak. So he doesn't have לא
אית ליה כסויא, lo it lei kisuya, שדר ליה גלימא ולא קיבל.
shadar lei glima velo kibel.
So he sent him a shirt, meaning רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel sent to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda a new shirt.
So he said okay fine, if he's not coming to the fast
day because he doesn't have a shirt, I'll send him a shirt.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is from a very
rich family. We know there are a number of stories of רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel who is either his father or his son depending
on which רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel it is and which רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel it is. They had a lot
of name switching, but they were
from, they were the נשיא's Nasi family. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel was
very rich. One time or a few times he
embarrassed רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, this just had to have been רבן
גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel son,
probably it's רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel the older רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel
son, right? And so we know there are three stories of when
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel embarrassed רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua in public and
then it became clear to him later, the סוגיא sugya in ברכות,
Berachot, it becomes clear to him later that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
is very poor and he apologizes and whatever and רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua chastised him for not really understanding the suffering of the תלמידי
חכמים talmidei chachamim who, who unlike רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel are not
from rich families and really do have to work very hard in
order to support their learning. So here רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, so
he sent him the shirt ולא קיבל, velo kibel, he didn't accept
it. Why? Presumably because he, he was either too proud, he wanted
to refuse, he didn't feel the need to accept this gift on
behalf of, from רבן שמעון גמליאל Rabban Shimon Gamliel because he felt
this, again, he was proud of this shirt that he had. He
said a ברכה bracha over it. It was something that made him
proud even if it wasn't, you know, his wife was out using
it so he couldn't use it to go to the תענית, ta'anit,
to the fast day, but that was enough for him. Now right
at the top of נ עמוד א. nun amud aleph.
Okay.
So דלי תפתא, dali tiftah, he raised up the mat that he
was sitting on. This is רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Okay. ואמר ליה
לשלוחא חזי מאי איכא. ve'amar lei lishlucha chazi mai ika. He said
to the messenger, look and see what's under here. Okay. If we
look in, sorry, fine, okay.
Yeah. חזי מאי איכא, chazi mai ika, look in the מפרש Mefarsh
on the second line. חזי מאי איכא ראה כמה עושר יש לי
שנעשה לי נס ונתמלא כל אותו מקום זהובים. chazi mai ika re'eh
kama osher yesh li shena'asah li nes venitmale kol oto makom zehuvim.
That he showed him that underneath the mat he actually, there had
been a miracle, oh my gosh, and he was sitting on a
huge pile of gold basically. And so look like I'm not actually
poor but I choose to dress this way because I don't, I
don't feel the need to associate myself with material, material things in
any real way. Okay. חזי מאי איכא. chazi mai ika. מיהו לא
ניחא ליה לאיתהנויי בהדין עלמא. mihu lo nicha lei l'ithenuyei behadein alma.
So because like I don't, I don't really need this. I don't
need to get this הנאה hana'ah from this world. Okay. And now
we have the story of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva getting married and
some of those stories. It's a similar סוגיא sugya to what appears
in כתובות Ketubot סב עמוד ב. samech bet amud bet. Interesting to
note some of the differences as well. Perhaps not for now but
to go back and compare.
Okay. רבי עקיבא איקדשה ליה ברתה דכלבא שבוע. Rabbi Akiva ikadsha lei
barteh deKalba Savua.
So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva married the daughter of כלבא שבוע. Kalba
Savua. כלבא שבוע Kalba Savua means the satisfied dog. It's a strange
name.
So some of the מפרשים mefarshim note that it might be that
people would come to him as hungry as a dog and he
would fill them up until they were שבוע, savua, until they were
satisfied. That he was very rich and prosperous. We know that he,
but again, it's not clear. Sometimes people have nicknames that we don't
really know where they come from. So he's כלבא שבוע. Kalba Savua.
So he's the, the satiated dog. So רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, yeah.
You probably look kindly upon this particular name as a dog owner.
Yes, possibly this is definitely, you know, there's nothing wrong with being
a happy and content doggie, have a big smile on your face.
Exactly. So רבי עקיבא איקדשה ליה ברתה דכלבא שבוע. Rabbi Akiva ikadsha
lei barteh deKalba Savua. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva married the daughter of
כלבא שבוע. Kalba Savua. שמע כלבא שבוע אדרה הנאה מכל נכסיה. shama
Kalba Savua adrah hana'ah mikol nichseih.
So then when כלבא שבוע Kalba Savua heard this he was very
upset because רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was poor and illiterate and he
was just a shepherd. So he took a נדר הנאה neder hana'ah
from all his property, meaning that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva should not
be able to get any הנאה hana'ah from his property, or possibly
even his daughter would not be able to get any הנאה hana'ah
from his property. This sort of explains what he's doing here, but
just, you know, we're in מסכת נדרים, Masechet Nedarim, but. Again, in
context, it's sort of a transition from one אגדתא agadata. *Agadeta* about
the תנאים Tannaim *Tanaim* to another. Okay. So he took this נדר
neder *neder*.
Was that הנאה *hana'ah* also and the tension between material pleasure and
spiritual pleasure?
For sure. רבי Rabbi יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* said I don't want to
get any הנאה *hana'ah* from things in this world.
הני *Hani*, in other words, it's interesting, it's a theological shift.
Right. So we're noting a number of different issues here with הנאה
*hana'ah*, with fasting, with poverty. So here now we have this story
of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* who again is going to
demonstrate incredible poverty and some challenging things about what a marital relationship
might look like, but it works for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi
Akiva*, I'm not sure it would work for many other couples. So
we'll see how that plays out. So, okay, הנאה מכל נכסי *hana'ah
mikol nechasai*, אזלא ואיתנסיבה ליה בציבתא *azla vehitnasiba lei betsivsa*.
So they went to recline, they went to basically to go live
in the straw house. הוה גנו בתיבנא *hava ganu beitivna*, right?
They were sitting in the בי תיבנא *bei tivna*, in the straw
house. הוה קא מנקיט לה תיבנא מן מזייא *hava ka menakit lei
tivna min mazaye* and he was taking out straw from the head
or from the hair. So the question some people are asking is
well who was taking the straw out of whose hair? The מפרש
*Mefaraish* says she would take the straw out of his hair. His
wife would take the straw out for him. But the ר"ן Ran
*Ran*, interestingly, perhaps a bit maybe more romantically for us who are
interested in רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*,
maybe more than his wife, although for a fact she's a very
interesting character in her own right, the ר"ן Ran, *Ran* says that
he would take the straw out of her hair. And again, this
is a question of sort of they were trying to beautify each
other, they were trying to still have some kind of relationship that
was even under the incredible pressures that this economic hardship gave them.
They had really no money, they were living with nothing.
They have a lot of straw. אמר לה Amar lah, *amar lah*
אי הוה לי *ei hava lei* רמינא לך *ramina lach* ירושלים דדהבא
*Yerushalayim de'dahava*. If רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* said to his
wife, if I had the money, if I was able to, I
would buy you a ירושלים דדהבא *Yerushalayim de'dahava*, ירושלים של זהב *Yerushalayim
shel zahav*. The משנה Mishnah *Mishna* in שבת *Shabbat* mentions a certain
kind of jewelry that the women in this time period had called
ירושלים של זהב *Yerushalayim shel zahav*, a Jerusalem made of gold. We
know now it's the title of a beautiful song.
But ירושלים של זהב *Yerushalayim shel zahav* or ירושלים דדהבא *Yerushalayim de'dahava*
is some kind of a circlet, a tiara made of gold with
maybe the shape of the buildings of ירושלים *Yerushalayim* or the shape
of the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* engraved on it in some way.
And so that would be a very beautiful piece of jewelry that
he wanted to give for her that he was unable to afford.
אתא אליהו *Ata Eliyahu*. So fine. So אליהו *Eliyahu* comes. Of course,
any good story אליהו *Eliyahu* has to come. אתא אליהו *Ata Eliyahu*,
אידמי להון כאנשא *idmei lehon k'inasha* and he appeared like a person.
דקא קרי בבבא *deka kari bevava* and he was knocking—he was calling
at the door. אמר להו amar lehu, *amar lehu* הבו לי פורתא
דתיבנא *havu lei porta de'tivna*, please give me some container of straw.
Ah, so here, what do they have? They happen to have straw.
Okay. דאיתתי ילדה *de'iteti yalda* אתא תיבנא *ata tivna* והבו לי *vehavu
lei*. So in other words they're saying דאיתתי ילדה *de'iteti yalda* and
לית לי *leit li* because they—that whoever has and לית לי *leit
li* that I don't have. מידם לאגונא *Midam l'aguna*, sorry, I don't—I
lost the place. Sorry.
Okay,
so the point is that this אליהו *Eliyahu* is coming, that he
doesn't have, okay, what? That even what they barely have, that he
doesn't have. Okay. אמר לה *amar lah* רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi
Akiva* לאינתתיה *l'intetei*, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* says to
his wife, חזי גברא דאפילו תיבנא לא אית ליה *chazi gavra de'afillu
tivna la it lei*. So look, there's a person who doesn't even
have straw. That we have straw, and he doesn't even have straw.
אמרה ליה amra lei, *amrah lei* זיל הוי בי רב *zil havi
be-rav*, so go learn תורה Torah *Torah*, his wife tells him. So
again, it's sort of like what's the transition between the first story,
the אליהו *Eliyahu* story about the straw, and then the second story
where she tells him to go learn in the בית מדרש Midrash
*Beit Midrash*? So maybe there's something there about she noticed his really
great personal character traits or something, he was still very generous even
though he had nothing, that oh, you need to become a greater
person, perhaps to note his generosity. But fine. So his wife says,
אמרה ליה amra lei, *amrah lei* זיל הוי בי רב *zil havi
be-rav*, go to בי רב *be-rav*. It's interesting to note in other
places in ש"ס Shas *Shas*, בי רב *be-rav*, the rabbi's house, it
sounds like it means elementary school. This story doesn't mention it, but
from אבות דרבי נתן *Avot de-Rabbi Natan*, another of the תנאים Tannaim
*Tanaim* sources, the story mentions about רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*
when he was forty years old and he was still illiterate, he
passed by and saw the water dripping on a rock. And he
said if the water can drip on the rock and can penetrate
in through the stone and break the stone down, and water is
soft and the stone is hard, then how much more so can
תורה Torah *Torah* be able to penetrate my heart which is like
a hard rock? And so he went to go study. at an
advanced age and he still became רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva
So in this story, it's his wife who encourages him to go
learn, so she says זיל לבי רב, zil lvei rav, okay, אזל
תרתי סרי שני. azal tartesrei shenei. He went for twelve years קמי
דרבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע, kamei d'Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Yehoshua, למשלם, l'mishlam, okay,
קמי דרבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע. kamei Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Yehoshua. So he
went to learn with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע. Rabbi
Yehoshua. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar,
רבי אלעזר בן ערך, Rabbi Elazar ben Arach, sorry, it's רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר בן הורקנוס Rabbi Eliezer ben Hurcanus and רבי
יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, two of the really the greatest of the תנאים
at the time, each known for different sorts of strengths in certain
ways. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua also often
disagree. So it's interesting to note that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was
learning from both of them. למשלם תרתי סרי שני, l'mishlam tartesrei shenei,
after twelve years had finished, קאתי לביתי, ka atei l'beitei, he came
to his house. שמע מן אחורי ביתיה דקאמר לה חד רשיעא לדביתהו,
shma min achorei beite de ka amar la chad rasha l'dvatayhu, so
he heard from behind the house, meaning he overheard them talking that
this certain רשיעא, rasha, terrible person, was saying to his wife, שפיר
עביד ליך אבוך חדא דלא דמי ליך,
shafir avid lach avuch
chada d'lo dami lach, that oh it's like it's really good what
your father said because you married somebody who's really not suitable for
you, because he's not around, meaning what, meaning you're still here poor
by yourself, your father said you can't have any of his property,
so you're here by yourself and your husband's been gone for twelve
years anyway, so really your father was right to deny you any
of his property. ועוד שבקך ארמלות חיות, ve od shavchak armalut chayot,
so and he's left you like a living widow כולי הני שני,
kulu hon shenei, all of these years. אמרה ליה, Amara lei she
said to him, אי צאית לדידי ליהוי תרתי סרי שני אחרינייתא, ee
tsayit l'didi l'havaei tartasrei shenei achranita, I would wish that he would
go and learn another
twelve years. אמר רבי עקיבא, amar Rabbi Akiva, since הואיל ויהבת
לי
רשותא אהדר לאחורי,
ho'il v'avid li reshu
ahadar l'achorei, so then רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva overhears this and he
says so look she gave me permission so I'm going to go
turn around right now and I'm going to go back and learn.
Won't you at least say hello? Right, so this is a question
everyone asks: how come he doesn't stop and say hello? It's a
difficult part of the story. Obviously even if she wants him to
go back and learn, how come he doesn't just go and spend
even a week or a month there at home and see how
she's doing?
Obviously an interesting question.
Again, this is sort of a parable and a fable in some
sense, not necessarily the way רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, necessarily lived with
his wife, that would be very difficult to understand.
Possibly
one message we can draw from it is the importance of continuity,
that a certain sense of learning for twenty-four years straight is not
the same as twelve years taking a break and doing another twelve
years. And so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva to a certain extent is
an extreme of that model, but that sense of continuity and keeping
through with things that we're doing when we're learning, when we're doing
מצוות, mitzvot, when we're busy with something, not getting distracted with other
possibilities. There's no such thing as multitasking, a lot of people have
told me. There isn't. So you can only really do one thing
at a time and if you're multitasking you're switching back and forth,
one thing and another thing, and your brain is always trying to
catch up. So if you're really focused on one thing and you
can keep going, then that's a way that's something that רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva could be teaching us here with this story. Again, it
can be very challenging to understand what does it really mean to
be married, you know, like the רשיעא rasha sort of sounds right
in this case. The רשיעא rasha said look you're an ארמלותא חייתא,
armaluta chayata, she's a living widow, it doesn't seem appropriate exactly that
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva should be dealing with his wife in this
way. Again, it was her choice, she permitted him to do it
that way. It's very challenging to understand. Yes.
No, I was going to say exactly, I mean I totally understand
that, you know, the idea of sacrifice for תורה Torah and whatever
it is, but you know then the question is at what cost?
Right.
And we sort of don't hear of רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva children
in such a way, you know, if he wasn't with his wife
for twenty-four years you can imagine they probably did not have such
an extensive family life. So that's a difficult a difficult question to
answer. And again, how did she earn her living? How did he
earn his living? What were they doing? He was in the ישיבה
yeshiva the whole time. But okay, so he comes back. הדר אזל
הוה תרתי סרי שני
אחרינייתא, hadar azal hava tartesrei shenei achranita, he went back for twelve
years. אתא בעשרין וארבעה אלפין זוגי תלמידי, ata b'esrin v'arba alfin zugei
talmidei,
he came back with twenty-four thousand pairs of students. And why does
it have to be twenty-four thousand? Because he learned for twenty-four years,
so there's one thousand students for each of the years that he
was learning.
Hopefully he did a little better as he got smarter.
Right, obviously exponential growth, but sort of again the numerical symbolism, twenty-four
hours there are in a day and twelve months in a year,
you know, some of these numbers have significance in terms of indicating
the passage of a large amount of time. נפקו כולי עלמא לאפיה,
nafku kulei alma l'apei, everyone came out to greet him. ואף היא
קמת למיפק, v'af hi kamat l'mifak, and she came to even to
greet him. אמר לה ההוא רשיעא, amar la hahu rashiya,
so that terrible רשיעא, rasha, the previous one from twelve years ago,
said ואת להיכא, v'at l'heicha, are you really married to this one?
אמרה ליה, she said to him, יודע צדיק נפש בהמתו. yodea tzadik
nefesh behemto. So
that
a צדיק tzaddik really knows what the animal is thinking. I don't
really know what this is exactly saying.
You mean even if someone can understand the נפש nefesh of the
בהמה, beheima, קל וחומר kal vachomer he should know my נפש, nefesh,
and like
how much she was
thinking about him.
For sure.
Or look, I've been living, or you could say it's like literally
I've been living like a בהמה beheima that I didn't have much,
but at least the צדיק tzaddik knows that much.
Maybe. And it has to do with the straw perhaps. It does
seem a bit somehow again sort of a strange
putting herself down.
Putting herself down, exactly. She's almost saying she's comparable to his בהמה
beheima in some way. Doesn't seem, again it seems a bit of
a strange story, but nonetheless, in other words, this רשע rasha is
asking, "Oh, your husband, that's the same רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that
you're married to that was such a, he didn't even come home
after however long and now he's become so famous and everything." So
okay.
Okay. אתא לאתחזויי לה, Ata l'itchazuyei lah, so he came
so she can go to see him. קא מדחן לה רבנן, Ka
medachan lah Rabbanan, so the רבנן Rabbanan were pushing her away. אמר
להו הניחו לה, Amar lehu hanichu lah, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
said to all of them, "Leave her alone, שלי ושלכם שלה הוא."
sheli v'shelachem shela hu. Everything that is both mine and all of
yours all belongs to hers, all attributed to her, because all of
רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva students owe everything to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva
and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva owes everything to his wife. So he
still notes in this one line he's really saying a great thank
you to his wife for enabling him to become the רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva who we know through the גמרא Gemara and through the
משניות, Mishnayot, but obviously a great sacrifice to herself in order to
enable her husband to reach those levels. You can imagine again some
of the great גדולין gedolim obviously also had difficult relationship with some
of their family members as well, navigating that relationship between a public
life and a life of real commitment to תורה Torah. and teaching
and learning at incredible amount of time every day comes at a
cost, something to think about. Okay.
But nowadays
there are a lot of רבנים Rabbanim who are spectacularly wealthy.
I'm thinking of graduates but particularly in some of the חרדי Chareidi
communities.
Well, because people make certain donations, people have certain
investments, sometimes or some people sadly are involved in various corrupt business
deals you hear in the news. So yeah.
Yeah, I was just thinking maybe it's a strange connection, but all
these students died during the twenty-four thousand. Right. And I wonder if
it's any pushback on the idea of what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
did in leaving his family, you know what I mean? Then he
raised the students who carry on the תורה Torah tradition after that.
That's a very interesting suggestion, that the forty-eight thousand students that are
here are the ones who end up dying in the plague and
therefore, and really later, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva can rebuild with five
students what he wasn't able to succeed in transmitting with so many
students, perhaps because he matured and learned a lesson, because the students
matured and learned a lesson. It's an interesting point. This is sort
of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva 1.0 and then there's going to be
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, 2.0. There's going to be a bit of
a different
approach perhaps. Okay. So
okay. שמע כלבא שבוע, Shama Kalba Savua, so כלבא שבוע, Kalba Savua,
his father-in-law hears, אתא ואישאיל על נדריה, ata v'isha'il al nidrei, so
he asked about his נדר neder because he had made a נדר
neder. some time. Ah, okay. So twenty-four years later רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva: has become such a great רבי Rabbi, and such a great
leader, and he's not this illiterate shepherd who had no money and
no prestige and no nothing that he thought his daughter had married.
Obviously his daughter was able to see the potential where he was
not. So he asks about his נדר. neder, ואישתרי אישתרי. V'ishtarei ishtarei.
So they totally said it's totally
fine. Why? Because a few different possibilities. So the problem here is
that we're going to see in a משנה Mishnah in a few
days in I think ס"ב, Samech-Bet, משנה Mishnah in ס"ב, Samech-Bet, did
I write it down? Yeah, משנה Mishnah in ס"ד. Samech-Dalet. The משנה
Mishnah in ס"ד Samech-Dalet says אין פותחין בנולד, ein potchin b'nolad, we
can't use new, new things which have arisen since the נדר, neder.
new conditions, new situations to create a פתח, petach, to create an
opening to be מתיר matir the נדר. neder So how could they
use the fact that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. had become so prominent
and great? And he's saying if I had known my son-in-law would
become such a great רבי, that
you had known even at the time he had this potential, I
wouldn't have taken it. So that's something that was never, that was
always there. You could.
Ah, okay. So right. So you have to say that really the
potential was already there to begin with. And that's again even more
than inspirational part of it.
He already had those משניות. Mishnayot.
So we had some משנה Mishna about that and we're going to
have more about it later. So that really shows us even more
about the potential and the greatness of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that
even when he was illiterate to a certain extent it was possible
to know that he would become great. And again his wife
knew. It really was a pre-existent condition in his character.
How are you translating this
אשתרי ואשתרי?
ishtarei v'ishtarei? So that's from the root שרי. shari. So שרי shari
means permitted.
But what's the פשט לשון peshat lashon meaning? Like why is it
אשתרי ואשתרי?
ishtarei v'ishtarei? Meaning it's short, meaning they're saying, whenever it's doubled it's
really emphatic. So they're saying it's totally undone, meaning immediately undone, totally
annulled it.
See the way they translate this here is that eventually he was
released from his oath, he had to do it a couple of
times. Maybe it wasn't so easy. Maybe exactly what you just said,
maybe because it was a
נולד.
nolad. I don't know where they're getting eventually from. Perhaps that's something
that the ר"ן Ran adds in. I know that the ArtScroll when
they translate they go by the ר"ן, Ran so I didn't get
a chance to look.
Well, they say also the הגהות יעב"ץ Hagahos Ya'avetz the word אשתרי
ishtarei should be deleted because then it would be...
Okay, so that's a possibility as well. We could check the different
כתבי יד kitvei yad and see. Fine. Okay. So משית
מילי איעתר רבי עקיבא. min shita milei i'atar Rabbi Akiva.
So how did רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva become rich? Six different ways,
six different kinds of treasures that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, was able
to uncover and how he became rich. So the first is מן
כלבא שבוע, min Kalba Savua, from his father-in-law, because his rich father-in-law
was then finally able to support him once he undid his נדר
neder because he became very proud of him and he wanted to
support him. Again, it's sort of strange to think about this character
shift in the father-in-law or maybe there was no character shift at
all. He always wanted a famous, prominent rabbi for a son-in-law, he
just didn't know that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was going to become
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva at the time. So that's a possibility. So
מן כלבא שבוע, min Kalba Savua, so כלבא שבוע Kalba Savua again,
where does the nickname come from? I don't really know. We could
come up with different theories. The second one, מן אילא דספינתא דכל
ספינתא עבדין לה מן עינא. min ila d'sfinta d'chol sfinta avdin leh
min eina. So now he got it from the mast of a
ship. So now we have to understand what are they talking about,
why would there be riches from a mast of a ship? Because
every ship עבדין לה מן עינא, avdin leh min eina, they make
a hiding hole in the mast of the ship. Unless somebody else
has a very different translation than mine. So they and basically what
would happen is that people on the ship might have to store
some of their money and things into this mast of the ship.
זמנא חדא, zimna chada, one time. Maybe it's smuggling. Okay, so that's
an interesting point, right? Okay, so זמנא חדא. zimna chada. Okay, so
we have a question what they're trying to. So now we're going
to tell us the story. So what happened? So זמנא חדא, zimna
chada, one time, אנשויא על כיף ימא, inshuya al kef yama, he
was going along the beach, okay, אתא הוא אשכחיה, ata hu ashkechei,
so he came along and he saw it, ומן גבזא דזמנא חדא
יהיב ארבע זוזי לספונאי. u'min gavza d'zimna chada yahiv arba zuzei l'sfunai.
So one time he gave four זוז zuz to a ספונאי, sfunai,
the shipyard guys, the whatever they're called, longshoremen or something, or the
sailors. אמר להו, אייתי לי מידעם. aiti li mido. So he says,
"Bring me back whatever you can bring back," presumably he's hiring them
to go catch him some fish or something. Okay. ולא אשכחו, v'lo
ashkichu, and they didn't find anything, אלא גבזא על כיף ימא, ela
gavza al kef yama, just this גבזא gavza on the beach. Which
of course they didn't open. Of course they didn't open, so they
found a treasure chest, right? Okay, so אתיוה ליה, atiyei lei, so
they brought it to him because he had hired them to bring
him whatever they find. Okay, so they're very honorable sailors. אמרו ליה,
amru lei, עביד מרנא עליה. avid maran alei. So they said to
him, "Our master should עביד מרנא עליה, avid maran alei, that he
should do to it, he should work on this." אשתכח דהוה מלי
דינרי. ishtakach de'hava malei dinarei. So he found that it was all
full of gold coins. So great, so רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva he
found a treasure chest. They found it. Yeah, they found the treasure
chest that he had hired them to bring back. And they didn't
open it and they didn't check. No, they didn't open it. Right.
But he doesn't have to return this lost property? So it's a
very good question, when you find a buried treasure is it really...
Oh, they found it in the sea, I mean... Again, this actually
comes up today. People who bring up these Spanish ships from the
16th century.
The original owner or the insurance company that insured them still owns
them. Now usually they will give a generous payment to the salvage
operation. But this is all established procedures. Well, and there's a question,
we have all these הלכות halachot about יאוש. ye'ush. I would think
with a lost object, by the time that this ship sinks in
the ocean that you would say יאוש, ye'ush, that there is really
יאוש. ye'ush.
Well, I don't know what it was like 2,000 years ago, but
500 years ago it clearly was not because this is actually how
Lloyd's of London got started. Right. And they would never consider it
to be completely lost. Right.
Because they know that it's down there.
Right. They know it's down there, they know approximately where it is.
Right. And they've been doing salvage operations for centuries. Right. It's just
they've been more practical in recent...
Right. So then the question becomes how much does a normal... you
know, if I had a sailing ship and it would break down
and crash, I would probably... again, it's a good question.
And what they generally do is they pay the salvagers very, very
handsomely.
Right. So those are interesting questions, you know, how we could write...
see if there are some תשובות Tshuvot about this or ask Rabbi
Limzer... you know, what does he think about buried treasure and salvage
operations? It could be an interesting series of תשובות. Tshuvot. Who knows?
Okay. So now we have another story about רבי עקיבא: Rabbi Akiva
זימנא חדא טבעת ספינתיה. Zimna chada tavat sfintayeh.
So one time his ship was being tossed and turned. דכוליה עיסקא
הווה מחיי בההוא גוזא. Dechuley iska hava machay behahu guza.
So they and they put all of the property, all of their
wallets and coins and everything into this, into this box. ואשתכח בההוא
זימנא דמן דסרוקיתא... Veishtakach behahu zimna demin Desarukita...
Sorry, I got confused a little bit.
No, it's at least here... They're trying to explain how this chest
was filled with gold coins.
Right, so right, at the time that this ship was all tossed
and turned that they put all the money into the chest. Right.
Okay. בההוא זימנא. Behahu zimna. At that time... דמן דסרוקיתא ומן מטרוניתא.
Demin Desarukita umin Matronita. No, no, no. The way they explain it
here is... let me read it from the...
at least the way they do it here is... זימנא חדא טבעת
ספינתא דמן סיקיתא. Zimna chada tavat sfinta demin sikita. So one time
this ship was from these סיקיתא Sikita people, whatever these סרוקיתא Srikuti
people are... These, you know... The way they explain this here is
Arabian traders. Let's think. וכולי עיסקא הווה מחיי בההוא גוזא. Vechuley iska
hava machay behahu guza. So whatever... whatever business they were doing, they
put in there. ואשתכח בההוא זימנא דמן סרוקותא. Veishtakach behahu zimna demin
srukuta. So then that one, that same chest was found by these
sailors and given to רבי עקיבא. And the fourth one is מן
מטרוניתא.
Min Matronita. Oh, and the מטרוניתא Matronita is the next case. Okay,
fine. So the... fine, okay. ומן מטרוניתא. Umin Matronita. So then also
from the rich woman. So what was the story of the rich
woman? So that you have to go to other סוגיות Sugyot to
find out. But basically רבי עקיבא does good with the rich woman
and she pays him back handsomely. This was a story the ר"ן
Ran I think quotes the whole גמרא. Gemara. Yeah. מן מטרוניתא. Min
Matronita. So the ר"ן Ran quotes the whole story here, the story
which is: פעם אחת הוצרך רבי עקיבא ותלמידיו מעות. Paam achat hutzrach
Rabbi Akiva vetalmidav maot. So they, רבי עקיבא and his students needed
money, so they need to go borrow money. והלכו אצל מטרוניתא. Vehalchu
etzel Matronita. So they went to this rich woman. אמרה לו לרבי
עקיבא הריני מלווה אותך ותהיה אתה לווה והקדוש ברוך הוא וים ערבים
בדבר.
Amra lo l'Rabbi Akiva hareni malva otcha v'teheh ata loveh v'Hakadosh Baruch
Hu v'yam
arevim badavar.
So you are going to pay me back but God and the
sea should be ערבים. Arevim. ערב Arev is a co-signer on a
loan or the guarantor on a loan. So if רבי עקיבא, if
you don't pay it back, then I will demand that God and
the sea will pay it back. An interesting way of saying it,
I'm not sure whether she really thinks that God or the sea
is going to pay back, okay, ערבים בדבר. Arevim badavar. קבע לה
זמן לפירעון. Kava lah zman l'piraon. So they fixed a time that
he would pay her back. וכשהגיע זמנה, Ucheshehigia zmana, when her time
came, הלכה אותה מטרוניתא על שפת הים. Halcha otah Matronita al sfat
hayam. At the time came then she went to the beach. אמרה
ריבונו של עולם. Amra Ribono Shel Olam. So she said to God:
גלוי וידוע לפניך שרבי עקיבא חולה. Galuy veyaduah lefanecha sheRabbi Akiva choleh.
You know that רבי עקיבא is very sick. What does that mean?
Is he really sick?
Guy, she's saying yeah, he was sick. I don't... again, I don't
know whether he's sick. We already saw yesterday that the rabbis are
often called sick because they kill themselves over studying תורה.
So I don't know, the ר"ן Ran says, the ר"ן Ran
says that he was sick.
I'm just reading the... Oh, yeah, yeah.
The ראש Rosh also
has a note ובזמן הפירעון חלה רבי
עקיבא.
uv'zman hapiraon chala
Rabbi
Akiva. All right. Okay, so anyway, he was sick.
Okay, I mean, we'll have to go see the... he's quoting from
another גמרא. Gemara.
So, okay, meaning when it says he's sick, he was sick. He
was sick. Okay.
גלוי וידוע לפניך שריבונו של... שרבי עקיבא חולה. Galuy veyaduah lefanecha sheRibono
Shel... sheRabbi Akiva choleh. רבי עקיבא is sick. ולא היה בידו לפרוע
חובו. Velo hayah beyado lifroa chovo. And you know that רבי עקיבא
can't pay back the loan. ראה שאתה ערב בדבר. Re'eh sheatah arev
badavar. So and I know that she saw that you, God, are
the ערב Arev בדבר. badavar.
מיד נשתטית בתו של קיסר.
Miyad nishtatit bito
shel Keisar. So the house of the... the daughter of the קיסר...
Keisar... נשתטית... nishtatit... was... she was... temporary insanity. Right, she became crazy.
ונטלה ארגז מלאה אבנים טובות ודינרי זהב וזרקה לתוך הים. Venatla argaz
mleia avanim tovot vedinari zahav vezarka letoch hayam. She took a whole
chest full of precious jewels and gold coins and threw it into
the city, into the sea. Presumably, it would sink. והים הביאתו במקום
שהייתה אותה מטרוניתא יושבת על שפת הים. Vehayam hevi'ato bemakom shehayta otah
Matronita yoshevet al sfat hayam. And the waves of the sea carried
the chest next to where this woman was sitting, okay. So, מיד
נטלה אותה ארגז והלכה לה. Miyad natla otah argaz vehalcha lah. So
she took the chest and she walked away. Meaning she prayed to
God and God paid back. her loan exactly like she expected, like
so God was the ערב. arev. Okay, so now what happened? Okay,
לימים נתרפא רבי עקיבא, leyamim nitrapa Rabbi Akiva, Rabbi Akiva got better
and so of course being honest Rabbi Akiva he's going to go
pay back his loan even if it's a little bit late because
he was sick, okay? He has a good excuse, he was sick.
ובא לו אצל ההיא מטרוניתא ומעותיו בידו לפרעון חובו u-va lo etzel
ha-hi matronita u-me'otav beyado lifra'on hovo and he brought the money to
pay back the loan, אמרה לו, amra lo, חזרתי אצל הערב, hazarti
etzel ha-arev, I went to the guarantor, God and the sea were
the guarantors, והוא פרע כל החוב ve-hu para kol ha-hov and he
paid back everything, והילך מה שנתן לי יותר ve-heilech ma she-natan li
yoter because he paid me back even more so I'm going to
give you even some of it because it shouldn't be mine, you
know, I only deserve what was paid back to me, okay. ומאותו
ממון שהחזירה לו נתעשר רבי עקיבא, u-me-oto mamon she-hehzira lo nit'asher Rabbi
Akiva, so the money that she gave back to him he got
very rich. Very interesting, I mean it obviously has to do something
with the sea, I mean there's like three things here at least.
There's yeah again I'm sure there's some uncertainty as to what it
was why are they coming up with like these six different explanations?
Well there are a few different explanations, you know he found a
treasure chest, he found a fish, I mean obviously he did all
of it, right? Well it says treasure chest and he found a
fish and a certain noblewoman who happened to get something from the
sea? Okay, so there's something about the sea. The sea is, you
know what I mean, the ברכה bracha that זבולון Zevulun got was,
you know, שפוני טמוני חול, sefunei tmunei chol, that things that are
buried in the sea become a source of riches people, yeah. Charlie
you have a question? It's interesting in this one line we have
two foreign words. What מטרוניתא matronita and סרוקיתא? sarukita? Yeah, סרוקיתא sarukita
is Greek and מטרוניתא matronita is Roman, it's like... yeah but they
come up all over the place, you know. מטרוניתא matronita is the
word for a rich woman, yeah. No but the point is obviously
there's something here and they're probably just trying to piece out what
it was. Perhaps, or they had different stories about Rabbi Akiva and
the אמוראים Amoraim put it together, you know. There were some stories,
I mean because you're just seeing one line, you know. Well because
they're referencing to other גמרות. Gemarot. This גמרא... Gemara... is this in
another גמרא? Gemara? I don't... I didn't check where it is because
the ר"ן Ran just quotes the whole thing so you don't have
to... so they expect you to know the whole story. I think
it's somewhere in the מדרש or something. I guess you have to
know all ש"ס Shas before you learn anything. Something like that. ומן
אשתו של טורנוסרופוס u-min ishto shel Turnusrufus so also the wife of
Turnusrufus. Turnusrufus was one of the Roman generals, Roman emperors and... the
big רשע. rasha. The big serious רשע, rasha, exactly and again the
ר"ן Ran quotes this story: פעם אחת בא לביתו שר וזעף אמרה
לו אשתו מפני מה פניך זועפים אמר לה מפני רבי עקיבא שמקנתר
אותי בכל יום בדברים אמרה לו אלוהיהם של אלו שונא זימה הוא
תן לי רשות ואכשילנו. pa'am ahat ba l'veito sar ve-za'ef amra lo
ishto mipnei ma panecha zo'afim amar lah mipnei Rabbi Akiva she-mekanter oti
be-chol yom bi-dvarim amra lo eloheihem shel elu sonei zima hu ten
li reshut ve-akhshilenu. So the wife of Turnusrufus tried, the wife of
Turnus... so she learned from בלעם Bilam presumably. So the story is
that oh the Jews are so terrible, their God doesn't like illicit
sexual activity and so the wife of Turnusrufus went to try to
seduce Rabbi Akiva and Rabbi Akiva was able to resist her and
because of that he was able to get rich. I don't... the
end of the story involves again finding some riches. We can look
in the ר"ן Ran later if we want to finish some more
of the גמרא Gemara so we don't have too much to do
tomorrow. So let's keep going. ומן קטיעא בר שלום. u-min Keti'a bar
Shalom. Keti'a bar Shalom again another story. This one I think is
the one about the monkey, is that right? That... okay we don't
have to go into that maybe we'll do a little bit more
research about some of these stories and come back tomorrow. Okay let's
keep going for now. And it says since he was the prominent
Roman who defended the Jews against annihilation by the Romans and therefore
he was put to death and he bequeathed his fortune to Rabbi
Akiva before he died. Oh that works so then it's not the
monkey. Oh the monkey story is coming up. Okay good. Okay. The
interesting thing is Turnusrufus, you know wasn't Turnusrufus the one that actually
killed Rabbi Akiva? Yes it says so. You have a bit of
a comeuppance here. Unfortunately there's some sense of that right that the
wife got involved and then it became it got ugly so... and
there's even a note that they got married later right? Right, so
that was part of the thing is that she decided to convert
or something because... ah so right that's the story is he because
when he met her he spit, or you can see in the
ר"ן it's like the narrow lines in the ר"ן by where the
תוספות Tosafot starts. So he spit and he cried and he laughed.
So she asked him why did you spit why did you cry
and why did you laugh? So he says: שניים אפרש שלישי לא
אפרש, shnayim a-faresh shelishi lo a-faresh, I'm going to explain two of
them and not explain the third one. רקקתי על שבאת מטיפה סרוחה,
rakakti al she-bat mi-tipa sruha, I spit because you came out of
a... though you're so beautiful, מטיפה סרוחה tipa sruha putrid drop but
the משנה Mishna says every person comes from a putrid drop so
presumably it's a reference to semen. בכיתי על האי שופרא דבלי בארעא
bahiti al hai shufra de-vali be-ara and I cried because such a
beautiful woman is going to in the end be interned in the
earth and your beauty will become nothing. והוא שחק שצפה ברוח הקודש
שעתידה להתגייר ולהינשא לו ve-hu shahak she-tzifa be-ruah ha-kodesh she-atida le-hitgayer ve-hinasei
lo and he he laughed because he anticipated he saw through רוח
הקודש Ruach Ha-Kodesh that she was going to convert and he would
marry her. Which also fits in with that other thing we had
if you're allowed to marry, you know what I mean, converting for
love. Converting for marriage. marriage and also interesting to note after all
of the story about רבי עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's relationship with his wife
now we have another story about רבי עקיבא marrying another woman. Again
sort of a strange story.
How does... did she die or like? I don't know how it
fits in you know, two wives, he became very rich, I don't
know the whole story.
Reminds me of רחב הזונה. Rahab HaZona.
Well let's keep going. We have only fifteen... what's in the composite
of her husband's jealousy part of the cause, it would be an
interesting theory.
Who knows? It's an interesting, you know, you would have to write
רבי עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's biography, you would have to pull together all
the different stories. This happened all over Rome.
This was routine. Men would steal each other's wives.
But let's keep going with the גמרא Gemara because we still have
a whole עמוד amud here and we
want
to make some progress before tomorrow. I know the אגדתא'ס Aggadatas are
very interesting, so we have to, you know, enjoy them and also
make progress as well.
So רב גמדא יהיב ארבע זוזי לספונאי לאתויי בהון... Rav Gamda yahiv
arba zuzei l'sipunai l'atuyei behon...
yeah, you have nothing at the end about this כתיה בר שלום?
K'tia bar Shalom?
כתיה בר שלום K'tia bar Shalom is I think it's also quoted...
it's in עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah on דף י', daf yud, so
if we want
we'll get there in a few years.
Okay, let's keep going. I'll bring it tomorrow. Okay. So רב גמדא
יהיב, Rav Gamda yahiv, so רב גמדא Rav Gamda gave four זוז
zuz to the sailors to bring back something.
Again the same kind of a thing.
Okay. לא אשכחו. Lo ashkechu. They didn't find anything. אתיי ליה בהון
קופא. Atuyei leh behon kofa. They brought him a monkey. Okay. אשתמיט
על לחרתא. Eshtamit al l'charta. He put him onto the onto the
beach, onto the ground. חפרו בתריה Chafru batrei and they dug after
him. אשכחוה דריבע על מרגניתא. Ashkechuha d'riva al marganita. And they found
that he was sitting on top of a pearl. So he said
like okay so he got rich after all, meaning he paid for
this and they just got him a monkey but then the monkey
was a pearl sniffing monkey. Okay. אייתינון ליה כולהון Aytinun leh kulhon
and they brought all of them to him. Again, the sailors are
very honorable sailors. The sailors bring back all of the pearls. אמרה
ליה בת קיסר לרבי יהושע... Amra leh bat keisar l'Rabbi Yehoshua... okay,
so now we have a new story. So אמרה ליה בת קיסר
לרבי יהושע בן חנניה. Amra leh bat keisar l'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananiah.
So the daughter of the Caesar, Roman Caesar, says to רבי יהושע
בן חנניה: Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananiah: תורה מפוארה בכלי מכוער. Torah mefo'arah
bichli mecho'ar. רבי יהושע בן חנניה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananiah was very
ugly and she said such beautiful Torah is stored in such an
ugly vessel. Now I wonder... this is Rabbi Yehoshua? רבי יהושע בן
חנניה, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananiah, yeah, Rabbi Yehoshua. The Rabbi Yehoshua? The
Rabbi Yehoshua who's Yehoshua ben Chananiah? Right, so this is Rabbi Yehoshua
and Rabbi Yehoshua was very ugly. We know some of the other
תנאים and אמוראים, Amoraim, some of them were very handsome. We know
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was supposed to be very handsome.
So Rabbi Yehoshua was very ugly. So she said תורה מפוארה בכלי
מכוער. Torah mefo'arah bichli mecho'ar. Why do you keep such beautiful Torah
in such or perhaps to God almost, why do you keep such
beautiful Torah in such an ugly vessel?
Interesting question why does the Roman Caesar, the daughter of the Caesar
think that the Torah is so wonderful?
Okay, I don't know a good answer to that, but she's very
interested in Judaism perhaps.
Okay, so he was a good teacher, who knows. So why do
you keep such beautiful Torah in such an ugly vessel?
אמר לה, he said to
her, למדי מבית אבוך במאי מנחיתו חמרא. Limdi mibeit avuch b'mai manchitu
chamra. So he said learn from your father's house, learn from the
Caesar's house, what do you keep your wine in? אמרה ליה במאני
דפחרא. Amra leh b'manei d'pachra. They keep it in earthenware jars, which
is the best, you know, the right thing to keep your wine
in, right? So he says אמר לה כולי עלמא בפחרא ואתון במאני
דפחרא? Amar lah kulei alma b'pachra v'atun b'manei d'pachra? Everyone keeps their
wine in earthenware jars and you in the emperor's house you keep
your wine in earthenware jars? אתון אחיתו במאני דכספא ודהבא. Atun achitu
b'manei d'chaspa v'dahava. No, you should put it into silver and gold
jars. Now everyone who has a little bit of a chemistry background
or even has had קידוש Kiddush in a silver cup on Friday
night knows that metal, metal can react with particularly red wine, but
really any wine and give it an off flavor. Right? You imagine
you would store your wine in a silver container, it would not
taste very good. Okay. אזלה ורמת חמרא במאני דכספא ודהבא. Azla v'ramat
chamra b'manei d'chaspa v'dahava. So she went and put all of the
wine into silver and gold jars וסרי v'sari and it became terrible,
it became bad. אמר לה אף אורייתא כן. Amar lah af Oraita
kein. So the Torah is like this as well. We know from
many other places in ש"ס Torah is compared to wine. Torah is
something that is good when it starts off and it gets better
with age. It grows, it improves. תלמידי חכמים Talmidei chachamim presumably get
deeper and wiser as they get older. The משנה at the end
of קידושין Kiddushin makes a similar point about תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah
that unlike other professions that you get worse at them as you
get older because you lose your strength and you lose your ability
to do fine physical tasks, but with תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah the
older you get you get sharper, you get wiser, the more you
work at it the better you are, which again is a reason
to keep studying and keep growing. Okay. So the wine went bad
and he says אף אורייתא כן. af Oraita kein. Okay. והאיכא שפירן
וגמירי? V'ha'ika shapiran v'gmiri? And and there are some people who are
both? Right? Okay. So she said there's some people who are very
beautiful and they also learn. So אמר לה אי הוו סנו הוו
גמירי טפי. Amar lah ei havu sanu havu gmiri tfei. If they
were ugly then they would be able to learn even better. Okay,
so in other words, you know, I'm ugly and I'm like this,
there are colleagues of mine who are also great scholars and they
are more handsome than I am, but if they were as ugly
as I am, they would be even even greater. He really was,
so this is an interesting point. Okay. ההיא דאתאי לקמיה דרב יהודה
מנהרדעא לדינא. Hahi de-atai lekamei de-Rav Yehuda min Nehardea le-dina. So a
woman came in front of Rav Yehuda in Nehardea. So this is
a story about Amoraim. A woman came to Rav Yehuda in Nehardea
for a judgment, ואיחייבת מן דינא ve-it-haivat min dina and she became
she was charged as guilty. She had to pay whatever it was,
guilty as charged, whatever it was. אמרה ליה שמואל רבך הכי דיינא
Amara lei Shmuel rabach heichi dayna would your teacher Shmuel have taught
this way, would have ruled this way? Rav Yehuda learned from both
Rav and Shmuel. So he had Rav as a teacher and Shmuel
as a teacher. So here she asks him about Shmuel. Shmuel was
the Rosh Yeshiva in Nehardea, so she was in Nehardea, so she
presumably knew about Shmuel. So she said שמואל רבך הכי דיינא Shmuel
rabach heichi dayna would he have really ruled like this? אמר לה
ידעת ליה Amar lah yadat lei did you know him? אמרה ליה
she said back to him, אין In of course I knew him.
קוצא ורבא כריסיה Kutza ve-raba keriseih he was he was short and
he had a very he was very obese, אוכמא ורבא שיני uchma
ve-raba shinei and what, he had a limp and very large teeth,
his teeth were all in there in his mouth. So אמר לה
ובבזוי קא אתית amar lah uve-vizui ka atit did did you come
in order to to embarrass him? Meaning if I were to ask
you did you know Shmuel, you know we have another story about
some of the Amoraim and one of the Amoraim comes from Bavel
goes to Eretz Yisrael and they they ask him you know oh
do you know about Rav or do so he says like oh
who do you learn by? Who's the who's the Rebbe there and
he says oh it's אבא אריכא. Abba Aricha. So you call him
אבא אריכא? Abba Aricha? I used to sit you know eight rows
behind Rav in the Yeshiva and he was amazing and he was
arguing so you call him by his first name you call him
you know Abba, how's it done you know. So this is coming
to say the same thing that this woman only noticed the physical
appearance of Shmuel but she didn't know his greatness in Torah. She
didn't recognize who who he really was. And again so she also
questioned Rav Yehuda's judgment on the case for the same reason she
didn't appreciate what he really learned from Shmuel. She only knew about
Shmuel you know the person she might have seen walking on the
street but not necessarily the teacher and the judge in this case.
Okay. דהוה ההיא איתתא בשמתא De-hava hahi iteta bi-shmata so he put
this woman in an excommunication. פקעה ומיתה Paka u-mita and she she
exploded and died. She blew up because when Rav Yehuda puts you
in the excommunication it gets pretty bad. Okay. So keep pressing on
for a few more minutes we'll try to get a little bit
more. So the last part here is again a bit strange. We're
going back to a discussion from the Mishnah about the ביצתא טורמייתא.
beita turmaita. The ביצתא טורמייתא beita turmaita some kind of a poached
egg dish so we're going to see what kind of this poached
egg dish is because we said even if you say a נדר
that you will not eat תבשיל tavshil you could still eat this
ביצתא טורמייתא. beita turmaita. מאי ביצתא טורמייתא? Mai beita turmaita? So what
is a this ביצתא טורמייתא? beita turmaita? אמר שמואל עבדא דעביד לה
שוי אלפא דינרי ומעלי אלפא זימני במיא חמימי ואלפא זימני במיא קרירי.
Amar Shmuel avda de-avid lah shavei alfa dinarei u-ma'alei alfa zimnei be-maya
chamimei ve-alfa zimnei be-maya kerirei. So you have to pay a thousand
coins for it. What you do is you take it a thousand
times in hot water and a thousand times in cold water. Hard
boiled egg. Some kind of a very overcooked hard boiled egg not
exactly sure. It takes a lot of effort to prepare. It takes
a lot of effort to prepare. Swell it down. Something like that.
עד דמזוטרא Ad de-mizutra until it shrinks very small. כי היכי דבלעתא
Ki heichi de-bal'ata when you swallow it. ואי אית כיבי סריך עלה
Ve-i it kivei sarich lah and when you have intestinal trouble then
it will absorb it. וכי נפקא אתיא Ve-ki nafka atya and then
it will take it out with it. It's some kind of medicinal
hard boiled egg. Okay but it was very fancy and very expensive
because it was very hard to prepare. Okay. Does it count as
cooked or something like that? It doesn't count as a תבשיל tavshil
because you don't eat it with bread or because I think or
it's a medicine. We said it was ביצתא טורמייתא beita turmaita was
compared to the case of if you say תבשיל שאיני טועם tavshil
she-eini to'em so this doesn't count as a תבשיל tavshil because we
said תבשיל tavshil was more or less something that's eaten with bread.
So what you'd have to know what is this thing, this is
some kind... A regular egg would be eaten with bread. A regular
egg that you would eat with bread that isn't this kind of
crazy egg then presumably. Okay. דאתיא דאתיא מאי סמא מתבעי ליה ובמאי
מתסייא? De-atya de-atya mai sama mitbe'ei lei u-ve-mai matsya? So then you'd
be able to use the egg in order to examine to to
do the diagnosis for your condition, yeah? Okay. שמואל הוה בדיק נפשיה
בקולחא Shmuel hava badik nafsheih be-kulcha עד. ad. He used the קולחא.
kulcha. Right. He used the קולחא. kulcha. קולחא kulcha is some other
kind of vegetable, right? So he would use the קולחא kulcha to
check himself to see sort of how he was doing. Okay. עד
דמסטרן אינשי ביתיה עליה סערתיהון ad d'mistaren inshei beiteih aleih sa'arteihon until
the people in his house were pulling out the hairs on their
head because they were so worried about how much pain he was
in. He did some kind of very painful medical procedure and everyone
else was worried about him so they were pulling out their hair.
Okay. תנן התם tanan hatam היה עושה בקלוופסין haya ose b'kluvsin לא
יאכל בבנות שבע. lo yokhal b'vnot sheva. So if we know the
Mishna teaches in מעשרות Ma'asros about a case of a person who's
working in a field there's a מצוה mitzvah from the תורה that
a person working in an orchard or in a vineyard of various
kinds is allowed to take a certain amount of the fruits that
he's harvesting while he's harvesting them, but if you're harvesting קלוופסין, kluvsin,
a certain kind of figs, you're not allowed to take בנות שבע,
vnot sheva, a different kind of figs because that's from a different
field or a different tree you're not allowed to take the one
that you're not working with. בנות שבע לא יאכל בקלוופסין. Bnot sheva
lo yokhal b'kluvsin. מהו קלוופסין? mahu kluvsin? What are קלוופסין? kluvsin? מידה
דתאני דעבדין מנהון לפתי. mida d'te'enei d'avdin minhon laftei. There are certain
kind of figs that you make out of them a kind of
jam. Okay. ההוא גברא דיהב עבדא לחבריה. hahu gavra d'yehav avda l'chavereih.
A person gave a slave to his friend לאגמוריה אלפא מיני לפתי
l'agmoreih alfa minei laftei to make for him a thousand different kinds
of fig jam. Okay. אגמריה תמני מאה. agmoreih tamnei me'ah. He made
only eight hundred kinds of fig jam. אזמניה לדינא azmanei l'dina and
he called him to a court case because he says it was
false advertising. You said that this slave could prepare a thousand kinds
of jam and he can only make eight hundred kinds of jam.
אזמניה לדינא לקמיה דרבי. azmanei l'dina l'kamei d'Rabbi. They call him before
Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi. אמר רבי, amar Rabbi, Rabbi says אבותינו אמרו נשינו
טובה avoteinu amru nashinu tova אנו אפילו בעינינו לא ראינו anu afilu
b'eineinu lo ra'inu meaning what even by my ancestors, I've tried this
thing like I tried it enough. I don't know what you're doing
about it why do you... You didn't try two hundred? I didn't
even see any of these eight hundred that you have. Right, exactly.
Like what are you doing? Rabbi is a wealthy person. Why are
you even trying this whole thing? You missed out on two hundred
kinds of fig jam? I don't get it. Okay. So רבי עבד
ליה הלולא לרבי שמעון ברבי. Rabbi avid lei hilula l'Rabbi Shimon b'Rabbi.
So Rabbi made a wedding feast for Rabbi Shimon b'Rabbi. Okay. כתב
על בית גננא עשרין וארבעה אלפין רבוון דינרין. katav al beit ganana
esrin v'arba'ah alfin ribvan dinarin. So they spent for the בית גננא
beit ganana the garden house, the wedding presumably the wedding canopy, 24,000
thousands of gold coins. They spent a lot of money for the
wedding feast. נפקו על בית גננא דנא. nafku al beit ganana dena.
They went out to the wedding canopy this one ולא אזמניה לבר
קפרא. v'lo azmanei l'Bar Kappara. And he didn't invite Bar Kappara. Oh,
I wonder why. Okay. אמר ליה amar lei אם לעוברי רצונו כך
לעושי רצונו. im l'overei r'tzono kach l'osei r'tzono. If it's going to
be like this for עוברי רצונו overei r'tzono for those who crossed
him right then how much more so for עושי רצונו osei r'tzono
those who do the way he wants. Okay. Because Bar Kappara said
to him about Rabbi על אחת כמה וכמה. al achat kama v'khama.
אזמניה. azmanei. So then I should invite him. אמר לעושי רצונו בעולם
הזה כך לעולם הבא על אחת כמה וכמה. amar l'osei r'tzono ba'olam
ha'zeh kach l'olam ha'ba al achat kama v'khama. So no, because if
you're going to spend this much on for this world and עושי
רצונו osei r'tzono so for good people for צדיקים tzadikim or whatever
that they're going to be able to get this fancy wedding feast
then עולם הבא Olam HaBa how much more so that it's going
to be even better. We'll start up from there again
tomorrow.
Maybe we'll say a little bit more about the אגדתא. So that's
the end of today.
Why did he not have invited Bar
Kappara?